<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<libraries xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<library>
  <libraryName>Alea: a library for reasoning on randomized algorithms in Coq</libraryName>
  <libraryOverview>
    <description>This library forms a basis for reasoning on randomised algorithms in the proof assistant Coq .
   The theoretical basis of this work is a joint work with Philippe Audebaud and is described in. 
   It is developed in the framework of the SCALP project (ANR-07-SESU-010) on Security of Cryptographic 
   ALgorithms with Probabilities. With respect to previous versions of this library, 
   the mechanism of type classes introduced by N. Oury and M. Sozeau [4] is used in order to represent 
   the order structure and the cpo structure on a given type. In this version, P. Courtieu started to 
   design simple automatic tactics for reasoning on measures, making an essential use of the possibility
   to rewrite under abstraction.
 </description>
 <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://scalp.gforge.inria.fr/" xlink:show="new">SCALP project</linkDescription>
 <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.msr-inria.inria.fr/projects/sec/certicrypt/index.html" xlink:show="new">CertiCrypt</linkDescription>
 </libraryOverview>
 <availableVersions>
   <version status="Current">
     <versionName>Version 8</versionName>
     <year>May 2013</year>
     <description>Compatible with Coq V8.4pl2. Also the development for positive real numbers has been slightly adapted.</description>
   </version>
   <version status="Previous">
     <versionName>Version 7</versionName>
     <description> This library also provides a livrary for positive real numbers represented with both integral part (in nat) and fractional part in [0,1].</description>
   </version>
 </availableVersions>
 <experimentalContentsOrExtensions>
   <contentDescription>This experimental library represents positive real numbers with an integral part 
   and a fractional part in [0,1]. It requires an extra axiom for decidability of 
   testing x≤ y in [0,1].</contentDescription>
   <content>
     <name>Markov</name>
     <description>A general library to implement a minimimalization algorithm for a decidable predicat P on natural numbers, assuming a proof of ∃ n, P n.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Markov.html" xlink:show="new">Markov</linkDescription>
   </content>
  <content>
     <name>Rplus</name>
     <description>An experimental representation of positive real numbers with integral and fractional part. 
     The real (n,1) is equal to (n+1,0). The four arithmetic operations are implemented and their main 
     properties proved. The exponential (with respect to a natural number) is defined as 
     well as bounded sum. A tactic Rpsimpl is defined to perform basic simplifications on expressions.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Rplus.html" xlink:show="new">Rplus</linkDescription>
   </content>
  <content>
     <name>RpRing</name>
     <description>Implementation of tactics Ring and Field on the set Rplus.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.RpRing.html" xlink:show="new">RpRing</linkDescription>
   </content>
 </experimentalContentsOrExtensions>
 <contributors>
   <contact>
     <name>Christine Paulin-Mohring</name>
     <contactsDescription>Main contact. LRI, UMR 8623 Univ. Paris-Sud 11, CNRS &amp; INRIA Saclay - Île-de-France</contactsDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lri.fr/~paulin#alea" xlink:show="new">Web page Link</linkDescription>
   </contact>
   <contact>
     <name>David Baelde</name>
   </contact>
   <contact>
     <name>Pierre Courtieu</name>
   </contact>
   <contact>
     <name>PROVAL Team</name>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://proval.lri.fr/" xlink:show="new">PROVAL Team</linkDescription>
   </contact>
 </contributors>
<contentFiles>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Misc</name>
     <description>A few preliminary definitions, in particular primitives for reasoning classically in Coq are defined.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Misc.html" xlink:show="new">Misc</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Cpo</name>
     <description>The definition of structures for ordered sets and ω-complete partial orders 
     (a monotonic sequence has a least-upper bound). We define the type O1→m O2 of monotonic functions and define the fixpoint-construction for monotonic functionals. Continuity is also defined.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Ccpo.html" xlink:show="new">Cpo</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Utheory</name>
     <description>An axiomatisation of the interval [0,1]. The type [0,1] is given a cpo structure: we have the predicates ≤ and ==, a least element 0 and a least-upper bound on all monotonic sequences of elements of [0,1].</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Utheory.html" xlink:show="new">Utheory</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/" xlink:show="new">The primitive operations</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Uprop</name>
     <description>Derived operations and properties of operators on [0,1]. This file defines a tactic Usimpl designed to help simplify expressions using operations on [0,1].</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Uprop.html" xlink:show="new">Uprop</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/" xlink:show="new">The main defined operations</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Monads</name>
     <description>Definition of the basic monad for randomized constructions, the type α is mapped 
     to the type (α → [0,1])→m [0,1] of measure functions. We define the unit and star constructions 
     and prove that they satisfy the basic monadic properties. A measure will be a function of type 
     (α → [0,1])→m [0,1] which enjoys extra properties such as stability with respect to basic operations, 
     continuity. We prove that functions produced by unit 
     and star satisfy these extra properties under apropriate assumptions.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Monads.html" xlink:show="new">Monads</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Probas</name>
     <description>Definition of a dependent type for distributions on a type α. A distribution on a type α is a record containing a function µ of type (α → [0,1])→m [0,1] and proofs that this function enjoys the stability properties of measures.
     We define the interpretation of specific random primitives : the distribution corresponding to a coin flip and the distribution corresponding to the random function which applied to n gives a number between 0 and n with probability 1/n+1.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Probas.html" xlink:show="new">Probas</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/" xlink:show="new">Stability Properties</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
 <contentFile>
     <name>Prog</name>
     <description>Definition of randomized programs constructions. We define the probabilistic choice and conditional constructions and a fixpoint operator obtained by iterating a monotonic functional. We introduce an axiomatic semantics for these randomized programs : let e be a randomized expression of type τ, p be an element of [0,1] and q be a function of type τ → [0,1], we define p ≤ [e](q) to be the property : the measure of q by the distribution associated to the expression e is not less than p. In the case q is the characteristic function of a predicate Q, p ≤ [e](q) can be interpreted as “the probability for the result of the evaluation of e to satisfy Q is not less than p”. In the particular case where q is the constant function equal to 1, the relation p ≤ [e](q) can be interpreted as “the probability for the evaluation of e to terminate is not less than p”.
We derive inference rules for this relation.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Prog.html" xlink:show="new">Prog</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>SProbas</name>
     <description>A relaxed notion of distributions called sub-distributions suitable to model programs 
     using both non-deterministic and random choice. A sub-distribution is not additive but instead satisfies 
     the following weaker properties.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.SProbas.html" xlink:show="new">SProbas</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/" xlink:show="new">Properties</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Cover</name>
     <description>A definition of what it means for a function f to be the characteristic function of a predicate P. Defines also characteristic functions for decidable predicates.
     This file uses the library Sets.v which defines sets as predicates and finite sets with an inductive definition.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Cover.html" xlink:show="new">Cover</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/Sets.html" xlink:show="new">Sets.v</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>BinCoeff</name>
     <description>Definition of binomial coefficients.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.BinCoeff.html" xlink:show="new">BinCoeff</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>Bernoulli</name>
     <description>Construction of a bernoulli distribution from the flip distribution.We prove that the probability of bernouilli(p) to answer true is exactly p. We use this distribution in order to simulate a binomial distribution such that Pr((binomial p n)=k) = Ckn pk(1−p)n−k.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Bernoulli.html" xlink:show="new">Bernoulli</linkDescription>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/" xlink:show="new">Example Program</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
  <contentFile>
     <name>IsDiscrete</name>
     <description>Proof that a distribution on a discrete domain is discrete. This result is adapted from the Certicrypt development.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.IsDiscrete.html" xlink:show="new">IsDiscrete</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
<contentFile>
     <name>DistrTactic</name>
     <description>This file introduces a tactic rsimplmu which attempts to simplify expressions involving randomized programs.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.DistrTactic.html" xlink:show="new">DistrTactic</linkDescription>
  </contentFile>
</contentFiles>
<downloads>
<download>
  <description>Source Files Downloads</description>
  <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lri.fr/~paulin#alea" xlink:show="new">Library Download Link</linkDescription>
</download>  
</downloads>
<requiredToolsForCompilation>
  <tool>
    <toolName>Coq</toolName>
    <toolDescription>The source files can be compiled using Coq version V8.3.</toolDescription>
    <toolLinkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://coq.inria.fr/" xlink:show="new">Coq Link</toolLinkDescription>
  </tool>
</requiredToolsForCompilation>
<examples>
  <example>
    <name>IterFlip</name>
     <description>A proof of probabilistic termination for a random walk. We consider the program
            let rec iter x = if flip() then iter (x+1) else x
         We prove that the probability that this program terminates is 1.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.IterFlip.html" xlink:show="new">IterFlip</linkDescription>
  </example>
  <example>
    <name>Choice</name>
     <description>A proof of composition of two runs of a probabilistic program, when a choice can improve 
     the quality of the result. Given two randomized expressions p1 and p2 of type τ and a function Q to be 
     estimated, we consider a choice function such that the value of Q for choice(x,y) is not less than Q(x)+Q(y). We prove that if pi evaluates Q not less than ki and terminates with probability 1 then 
     the expression choice(p1,p2) evaluates Q not less than k1(1−k2)+k2 (which is greater than both k1 and k2 
     when k1 and k2 are not equal to 0).</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.Choice.html" xlink:show="new">Choice</linkDescription>
  </example>
  <example>
    <name>RandomList</name>
     <description>Construction of a distribution to pick uniformely an element in a list.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/ALEA.RandomList.html" xlink:show="new">RandomList</linkDescription>
  </example>
<example>
    <name>ProbTuring</name>
     <description>A simple formalisation of probabilistic Turing machines in ALEA.</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/examples/ProbTuring.html" xlink:show="new">ProbTuring</linkDescription>
  </example>
<example>
    <name>Ycart</name>
     <description>Evaluation of probability of termination for a program adapted from an example due to B. Ycart, parameterized by a function K of type nat→ nat and a natural number N.
        let rec ycart n = if random N &lt; K n then n else ycart (n+1)
        Probability of termination of (ycart n) is shown to be equal to ∏k=n∞ (1−F k), with F n=K n/(1+N).</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/examples/Ycart.html" xlink:show="new">Ycart</linkDescription>
  </example>
<example>
    <name>AbstractWalk</name>
     <description>proof of termination of a special walk where with a bounded positive probability we strictly decrease the size of the object in the call (otherwise we call the procedure on the same object).</description>
     <linkDescription xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lri.fr/~paulin/ALEA/html/examples/AbstractWalk.html" xlink:show="new">AbstractWalk</linkDescription>
  </example>
</examples>
<references>
  <reference>
    <description>Philippe Audebaud and Christine Paulin-Mohring. Proofs of randomized algorithms in Coq. 
    Science of Computer Programming, 74(8):568–589, 2009. 
    A preliminary version appeared in the proc. of MPC 06.</description>
  </reference>
 <reference>
    <description>Dexter Kozen. Semantics of probabilistic programs. J. of Computer and System Science, 1981.</description>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <description>Dexter Kozen. A probabilistic PDL. In 15th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing, 1983.</description>
  </reference>
<reference>
    <description>Matthieu Sozeau and Nicolas Oury. First-Class Type Classes. In Sofiène Tahar, Otmame Ait-Mohamed, and César Muñoz, editors, 21th International Conference on Theorem Proving in Higher Order Logics, LNCS. Springer-Verlag, August 2008.</description>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <description>The Coq Development Team. The Coq Proof Assistant Reference Manual – Version V8.3, 2010.</description>
  </reference>
</references>
</library>
</libraries>
